<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The charter of the Bahama Islands</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08738</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3724AA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R173810</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">62369106</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 62369106</idno>
            <idno type="VID">187838</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08738)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 187838)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2846:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The charter of the Bahama Islands</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II).</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bahamas --  Politics and government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bahamas --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Colonies --  North America --  Administration --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="charter">
            <pb facs="tcp:187838:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:187838:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:187838:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE CHARTER OF THE <hi>BAHAMA</hi> Iſlands.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>CHARLES</hi> the Second, by the Grace of GOD, King of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To All to whom theſe preſents ſhall come greeting.</p>
            <p>KNOW YEE That We for divers good Cauſes and Conſiderations, us, hereunto eſpecially moving, of our eſpecial Grace, certain Knowledge, and meer Motion: HAVE Given and Granted, and by theſe Preſents, for us, our Heirs and Succeſſors, DO Give and Grant unto our Right truſty and Right intirely Beloved Coſen <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle;</hi> our Right truſty and Right Well-beloved Coſen and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour <hi>William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven;</hi> our Right truſt and Well-beloved Councellours, <hi>John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Chancellour and Under-Treaſurer
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:187838:3"/>of our Exchequer; Sir <hi>George Carterett</hi> Knight, and Baronet, Vice-Chamberlain of our Houſhold; and our Truſty and Well-beloved Sir <hi>Peter Colleton</hi> Baronet, their Heirs and Aſſigns. All thoſe Iſlands called <hi>Baha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,
<note place="margin">The Bounds</note> Clentheria, Vianis, Providence, Inagua,</hi> and all other thoſe Iſlands lying in the Degrees of Twenty and two, to Twenty and ſeven North Latitude, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly known by the Name of the <hi>Bahama Iſlands,</hi> or the Iſlands of the <hi>Lucayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together, with all and ſingular Ports, Harbours, Bays, Rivers, and Iſlets belonging unto the Iſlands afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; with the Fiſhing of all Sorts of Fiſh; Whales, Sturgeons, and all other Royal Fiſhes in the Sea, Bays, Iſlets, and Rivers within the Premiſes; and the Fiſh therein taken: Together with the Royalty of the Sea upon the Coaſt within the Limits aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And moreover, All Vains, Mines, and Quarries, as well diſcovered as not diſcovered, of Gold, Silver, Gems, precious Stones, and all other whatſoever, be it of Stones, Mettals, or any other thing whatſoever found, or to be found within the Iſlands and Limits aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And furthermore, The Patronage and Avowſons of all the Churches and Chapels (which as Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſhall increaſe) within the Iſlands, Iſles, Iſlets, and Limites aforeſaid ſhall happen hereafter to be Erected; together with Licenſe and Power to Build and Found Churches, Chapels, and Oratories in convenient and fit Places within the ſaid Bounds and Limits, and to cauſe them to be Dedicated and Conſecrated according to the Eccleſiaſtical Laws of our Kingdom of <hi>England:</hi> Together with all and ſingular the like, and as ample Rights, Juriſdictions, Priviledges, Prerogatives, Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alties Liberties, Immunities, and Franchiſes of what kind ſoever with in the Iſlands, Iſles, Iſlets, and Limits aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>To Have,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Juriſdict. of a Count</hi> Palatine.</note> Uſe, Exerciſe and Enjoy; the ſame as amply fully, and in as ample manner as any Biſhop of <hi>Durham</hi> in our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> ever heretofore Held, Uſed, or Enjoyed; or of Right ought or could Have, Uſe, or Enjoy.</p>
            <p>And them, The ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:187838:3"/>Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> their Heirs and Aſſigns.</p>
            <p>We do by theſe Preſents, for us, our Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, Make, Create, and Conſtitute the true and abſolute Lords and Proprietors of the ſaid Iſlands; and of all other, the Premiſes, ſaving always the Faith, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance, and Soveraign Dominion due to us, our Heirs and Succeſſors, for the ſame.</p>
            <p>To Have, and to Hold, Poſſeſs, and Enjoy the ſaid Iſlands, Iſles, Iſlets, and all and ſingular other the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, unto them the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton,</hi> their Heirs and Aſſigns for ever.</p>
            <p>To be Holden of us, our Heirs, and Succeſſors,
<note place="margin">Tenure.</note> as of our Mannor of <hi>Eaſt-Greenwick</hi> in our County of <hi>Kent,</hi> in free and common Soccage, and not <hi>in Capite,</hi> or by Knights-ſervice: Yielding and paying yearly to us, our Heirs and Succeſſors for the ſame, the Fourth part of all Gold and Silver Oar, which within the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits hereby granted, ſhall from time to time happen to be found. And alſo Yeilding and paying to us, our Heirs and Succeſſors as often as we or they ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to come or enter in to the ſaid Iſlands, one Pound of fine Silver.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as we have Made and Ordained the aforeſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton,</hi> their Heirs and Aſſigns, the True Lords and Proprietors of the Iſlands aforeſaid: <hi>Know ye</hi> therefore moreover that we repoſing eſpecial Truſt and Confidence in their Fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Wiſdom, Juſtice, and Provident Circumſpection for us, our Heirs and Succeſſors. Do Grant full and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Power by Vertue of theſe Preſents, to them the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton,</hi> and their Heirs and Aſſigns, for the good and happy Government of the ſaid Iſlands, full Power and Authority to Erect, Conſtitute, and make ſeveral Counties, Baronies, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:187838:4"/>Colonies, of, and within the aforeſaid Iſlands, Lands, and Hereditaments, in, and by theſe Preſents granted, or mentioned to be granted as aforeſaid, with ſeveral and diſtinct Juriſdictions, Power, Liberties and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges: And alſo to Make, Ordain, and Enact, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their Seals to publiſh any Laws and Conſtitutions whatſoever, either appertaining to the Publick Eſtate of the ſaid Iſlands, or of any diſtinct or particular Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Barony, or Colony, of or within the ſame, or to the private Utility of particular Perſons, according to their beſt Diſcretion, by and with the Advice, Aſſent and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of the Free-Men of the ſaid Iſlands, or of the Free-Men of the County, Barony, or Colony for which ſuch Laws or Conſtitution ſhall be made, or of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of them, or of their Delegates or Deputies, whom for Enacting of the ſaid Laws, When, and as often as need ſhall require. We Will, that the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton,</hi> and their Heirs and Aſſigns, ſhall from time, to time, Aſſembled in ſuch Manner and Form as to them ſhall ſeem beſt; and the ſame Law duely to Execute upon the People within the ſaid Iſlands, County, Barony, or Colony, and the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits thereof for the time being, or which ſhall be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted under the Power or Government of them, or any of them; either ſailing towards the ſaid Iſlands, or returning from thence towards <hi>England,</hi> or any other of ours or Forreign Dominions, by Impoſition of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, Impriſonment, or any other Puniſhment. Yea, if it ſhall be needful, and the quality of the Offence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it, by taking away Member and Life, either by them the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>Georege Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton,</hi> and their Heirs, or by them or their Deputies, Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, Judges, Juſtices, Magiſtrates, Officers and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to be Ordained or Appointed according to the Tenor and true intention of theſe Preſents. And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to Erect and make any Court or Courts whatſoever of Judicature or otherwiſe, as ſhall be requiſite; and to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:187838:4"/>Appoint and Eſtabliſh any Judges, or Juſtices, Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, or Officers whatſoever, as well within the ſaid Iſlands as at Sea, in ſuch Manner and Form as unto the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton,</hi> or their Heirs ſhall ſeem moſt convenient: Alſo to Remit, Releaſe, Pardon and Aboliſh, either before Judgment or after, all Crimes and Offences whatſoever againſt the ſaid Laws, and to do all and every other thing and things which unto the compleat Eſtabliſhment of Juſtice unto Courts, Seſſions, and Forms of Judicature and Manners of proceedings therein do belong, although in theſe Preſents expreſs Mention is not made thereof, and by Judges by him or them delegated to Award, Proceſs, hold Pleas, and determine in all the ſaid Courts and Places of Judicature, all Actions, Suits, and Cauſes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, as well Criminal as Civil, Real, Mixt, Perſonal, or of any other kind or nature whatſoever; which Laws ſo as aforeſaid to be Publiſhed. Our will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is, and we do enjoyn, require and command, ſhall be abſolute, Firm, and Available in Law; and that all the Leige People of us, our Heirs and Succeſſors within the ſaid Iſlands; do obſerve and keep the ſame inviol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably in thoſe Parts ſo far as they concern them, under the Pains and Penalties therein expreſſed, or to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed: Provided nevertheleſs that the ſaid Laws be conſonant to Reaſon, and as near as may be convenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agreeable to the Laws and Cuſtoms of this our Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And becauſe ſuch Aſſemblies of Free-holders cannot be ſo ſuddainly called as there may be occaſion to require the ſame: We do therefore by theſe Preſents, Give and Grant unto the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton;</hi> their Heirs and Aſſigns by themſelves or their Magiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates in that behalf lawfully Authorized, full Power and Authority from time to time, to make and ordain fit and wholſome Orders and Ordinances within the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Iſlands, or any County, Barony or Province, of,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:187838:5"/>or within the ſame, to be kept and obſerved as well for the keeping of the Peace, as for the better Government of the People there abiding, and to publiſh the ſame to All to whom it may concern, which Ordinance we do by theſe Preſents ſtrictly Charge and Command to be inviolably obſerved within the ſaid Iſlands under the Penalties therein expreſſed, ſo as ſuch Ordinances be reaſonable and not repugnant or contrary, but as near as may be agreeable to the Laws and Statutes of this our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and ſo as the ſame Ordinances do not extend to the binding, charging or taking away of the Rights or Intereſt of any Perſon or Perſons, in their Free-hold, Goods, or Chattels, whatſoever.</p>
            <p>And to the end, the ſaid Iſlands may be the more happily encreaſed by the multitude of People reſorting thither, and may likewiſe be the more ſtrongly defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Incurſions of <hi>Salvages</hi> and other <hi>Enemies, Pirates</hi> and <hi>Robbers:</hi> Therefore, we for us, our Heirs, and Succeſſors, do Give and Grant by theſe Preſents, Power, Licenſe, and Liberty unto all the liege People of us, our Heirs, and Succenors, in our Kingdom of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> or elſewhere within any other our Dominions, Iſlands, Colonies, or Plantations, (excepting thoſe who ſhall be eſpecially forbidden) to tranſport themſelves and Families into the ſaid Iſland with convenient Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and, fitting Proviſions, and there to ſettle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, Dwell, and Inhabit any Law, Act, Statute, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, or other Thing to the contrary in any wife notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And we will alſo, and of our more eſpecial Grace, for us, our Heirs, and Succeſſors, do ſtrictly Enjoyn, Ordain, Conſtitute and Command, that the ſaid Iſlands, ſhall be of our Allegiance, and that all and ſingular the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and Liege People of us, our Heirs and Succeſſors, tranſported, or to be tranſported into the ſaid Iſlands, and the Children of them, and ſuch as ſhall deſcend from them, there born, or hereafter to be born, be, and ſhall be Denizons and Leiges of us, our Heirs, and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, of this our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and be in all things Held, Treated, and Reputed as the leige faithful People of us, our Heirs and Succeſſors, born within this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:187838:5"/>our ſaid Kingdom, or any other of our Dominions, and may inherit, or otherwiſe purchaſe and receive take, have, hold, buy and poſſeſs any Lands, Tenements, or Hereditaments within the ſaid Places, and them may Occupy, and Enjoy, Give, Sell Alien, and Bequeath: As likewiſe, all Liberties, Franchiſes, and Privileges, of this our Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> and of other our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions aforeſaid; may freely and quietly have, Poſſeſs, and Enjoy, as our leige People, born within the ſame, without the moleſtation, lett, vexation, trouble or grievance, of us, our Heirs and Succeſſors, any Statute, Act, Ordinance, or Proviſions to the contrary not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding.</p>
            <p>And farthermore, that our Subjects of this our ſaid Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and other our Dominions, may be the rather incouraged to undertake this Expedition, with ready and cheerful mind; <hi>Know Yee,</hi> That we of our eſpecial Grace, certain Knowledg, and meer Motion, do Give and Grant, by vertue of theſe Preſents, as well as to the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton,</hi> and their Heirs, as unto all others as ſhall from time to time repair unto the ſaid Iſlands, with a purpoſe to inhabit there, or to trade with the Natives thereof, free Liberty and Licenſe to Lade and Fraight in any Ports whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, of us, our Heirs and Succeſſors,
<note place="margin">Licenſe to tranſport Goods and Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe.</note> and into the ſaid Iſlands, by them then Servantsand Aſſigns, to tranſport, all and ſingular their Goods, Wares, and Merchandizes; as likewiſe all ſorts of Grain whatſoever, and any other Thing whatſoever, neceſſary for their Food and Cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (not prohibited by the Laws and Statutes of our Kingdoms and Dominions to be carried out of the ſame without any lett, or moleſtation of us, our Heirs and Succeſſors, or of any other our Officers and Miniſters whatſoever) ſaving alſo, to us, our Heirs and Succeſſors, the Cuſtoms, and other Duties and Payments due for the ſaid Wares and Merchandizes, according to the ſeveral Rates of the Places from whence the ſame ſhall be Tranſported.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:187838:6"/>
            <p>We will alſo, and by theſe Preſents, for us, our Heirs and Succeſſors, do give, and grant Licenſe by this our Charter, unto the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albermarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton,</hi> their Heirs and Aſſigns, and to all the Inhabitants and Dwellers in the Iſlands aforeſaid, both preſent and to come, full Power, and abſolute Authority to import or unlade by themſelves, or their Servants, Factors, or Aſſigns, all Merchandizes and Goods whatſoever that ſhall ariſe of the Fruits and Commodities of the ſaid Iſlands, either by Land, or Sea, into any the Ports of us, our Heirs and Succeſſors, in our Kingdom of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> or otherwiſe to diſpoſe of the ſaid Goods in the ſaid Ports; and if need be, within one Year next after the unlading to lade the ſaid Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes and Goods again into the ſame, or other Ships, and to Export the ſame into any other Countries, either of our Dominions or Forreign, (being in Amity with us, our Heirs and Succeſſors) ſo as they pay ſuch Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, Subſidies, and other Duties for the ſame, to us, our Heirs and Succeſſors, as the reſt of the Subjects of this our Kingdom for the time being ſhall be bound to pay, beyond which, we will not that the Inhabitants of the ſaid Iſlands ſhall be any way Charged: <hi>Provided</hi> nevertheleſs, and our Will and Pleaſure is, and we have further for the conſiderations aforeſaid, of our eſpecial Grace, Certain Knowledg, and meer Motion, given and Granted, and by theſe Preſents, for us, our Heirs and Succeſſors. Do Give and Grant unto the ſaid <hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton;</hi> their Heirs and Aſſigns, full and free Licenſe, Liberty, Power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority at any time or times, from and after the Feaſt of St. <hi>Michael the Archangel,</hi> next enſuing, the date hereof to Export and carry out of any of our Dominions into the ſaid Iſlands Cuſtom free, all Sorts of Tools which ſhall be uſeful and neceſſary for the Planters there in the Accommodation and Improvement of the Premiſes, any thing before in theſe Preſents contained,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:187838:6"/>or any Law, Act, Statute, Prohibition, or other Matter or Thing heretofore Had, Made, Enacted, or Provided; or hereafter to be Had, Made, Enacted, or Provided, or the contrary in any wiſe Notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And Furthermore, of our more ample and eſpecial Grace, certain Knowledg, and meer Motion, we do for us, our Heirs and Succeſſors, Grant unto the ſaid <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton;</hi> their Heirs and Aſſigns, full and abſolute Power and Authority to Make, Erect, and Conſtitute within the ſaid Iſlands, and the Iſles and Iſlets aforeſaid, ſuch and ſo many Sea Ports, Harbours, Creeks, and other Places for diſcharge and unlading of Goods and Merchandizes out of Ships, Boats, and other Veſſels; and for lading them in ſuch and ſo many Places, and with ſuch Juriſdictions, Priviledges, and Franchiſes unto the ſaid Ports belonging as to them ſhall ſeem moſt expedient: And that all and ſingular the Ships, Boats, and other Veſſels, which ſhall come for Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizes and Trade into the ſaid Iſlands, or ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of the ſame, ſhall be laden and unladen at ſuch Ports only as ſhall be Erected and Conſtituted by the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton,</hi> their Heirs and Aſſigns, and not elſewhere any Uſe, Cuſtom, or any thing to the contrary in any wiſe Notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And we do furthermore Will, Appoint and Ordain, and by theſe Preſents for us, our Heirs and Succeſſors, do Grant unto the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Authony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton;</hi> their Heirs and Aſſigns. That they the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton;</hi> their Heirs and Aſſigns, may from time to time for ever,
<note place="margin">Power to Aſſeſs Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms.</note> have and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the Cuſtoms and Subſidies in the Ports. Harbours, Creeks, and other places within the aforeſaid Iſlands, payable for Goods, Merchandizes, and Wares there
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:187838:7"/>laded, or to be laded, or unladed, the ſaid Cuſtoms to be reaſonably Aſſeſſed upon any occaſion by themſelves, and by and with the conſent of the Free People there, or the greater part of them as aforeſaid. To whom we give Power by theſe Preſents, for us, our Heirs and Succeſſors, upon juſt Cauſe and in a due proportion to Aſſeſs and Impoſe the ſame.</p>
            <p>And further, of our eſpecial Grace, certain Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg,
<note place="margin">Power to Create Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nures.</note> and meer Motion, we have Given, and Granted, and by theſe Preſents for us, our Heirs and Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, do Give, Grant, unto the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton;</hi> their Heirs and Aſſigns, full and abſolute Licenſe, Power and Authority. That they the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Lord <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkely, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton;</hi> their Heirs and Aſſigns, from time to time hereafter for ever, at his, and their Will and Pleaſure, may Aſſign, Alien, Grant, Demiſe, or Enfeoff the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes or any part or parcel thereof, to him or them, that ſhall be willing to purchaſe the ſame, and to ſuch Perſon, and Perſons as they ſhall think fit, To have and to hold to them the ſaid Perſon, or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, their Heirs and Aſſigns in Fee Simple, or Fee Tail or for Term of Life, or Lives, or Years, to be held of them the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton,</hi> their Heirs and Aſſigns, by ſuch Rents, Services, and Cuſtoms, as ſhall ſeem fit to the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton;</hi> their Heirs and Aſſigns; and not immediately of us, our Heirs and Succeſſors: And to the ſame Perſon, or Perſons, and to all and every of them, we do Give and Grant by theſe Preſents for us, our Heirs and Succeſſors, Licenſe, Authority, and Power, that ſuch Perſon, or Perſons may have and take the Premiſes, or any
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:187838:7"/>Parcel thereof, of the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton;</hi> their Heirs and Aſſigns, and the ſame to hold to themſelves, their Heirs or Aſſigns, in what Eſtate of Inheritance ſoever, in Fee Simple, or in Fee Tail, or otherwiſe, as to them, the ſaid <hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton;</hi> their Heirs and Aſſigns ſhall ſeem expedient: The Statute in the Parliament of <hi>Edward</hi> Son of King <hi>Henry,</hi> hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore King of <hi>England,</hi> our Predeceſſor, commonly called the Statute of <hi>Quia emptores terrarum,</hi> or any other Statute, Act, Ordinance, Uſe, Law, Cuſtom, or any other Matter, Cauſe, or thing heretofore Publiſhed or Provided to the contrary, in any wiſe notwithſtanding: And becauſe many Perſons born or inhabiting in the ſaid Iſlands for their Deſert and Services, may expect and be capable of Marks of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Favour, which in reſpect of the great Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance cannot conveniently be conferred by us. Our Will and Pleaſure therefore is, and we do by theſe Preſents, Give, and Grant, unto the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven,
<note place="margin">Power to Confer Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</note> John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton;</hi> their Heirs and Aſſigns, full Power and Authority to Give, and Confer unto, and upon ſuch of the Inhabitants of the ſaid Iſlands, as they ſhall think, do, or ſhall Merit the ſame, ſuch Marks of Favour and Titles of Honour as they ſhall think fit, ſo as thoſe Titles or Honour be not the ſame as are enjoyned by, or conferred upon any the Subjects of this our Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further, alſo we do by the Preſents, for us, our Heirs and Succeſſors, Give, and Grant Licenſe to them the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton;</hi> their Heirs and Aſſigns, full Power, Liberty, and Licenſe to Erect, Raiſe, and Build within the ſaid
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:187838:8"/>Iſlands and Places aforeſaid, or any Part, or Parts thereof, ſuch and ſo many Forts, Fortreſſes, Caſtles, Cities, Boroughs, Towns, Villages, and other Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications whatſoever; and the ſame or any of them to fortifie and furniſh with Ordinance, Powder, Shot, Armour, and all other Weapons, Amunition, and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliments of War, both Offenſive, and Defenſive, as ſhall be thought fit and convenient for the ſafety and welfare of the ſaid Iſlands, or any part thereof, and the ſame or any of them from time to time, as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſhall require to Diſmantle, Disfurniſh, Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and pull down. And alſo to Place, Conſtitute, and Appoint, in, or over all or any of the ſaid Caſtles, Forts, Fortifications, Cities, Towns, and Places a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid; Governours, Deputy-Governours, Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, Sheriffs, and other Officers, Civil, and Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, as to them ſhall ſeem meet. And to the ſaid Cities, Boroughs, Towns, Villages, or any other Place, or Places within the ſaid Iſlands, to Grant Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters or Charters of Incorporation; with all Liberties, Franchiſes and Priviledges requiſite and uſual, or to, or within any Corporations within this our Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> granted or belonging, and in the ſame Cities, Boroughs, Towns, and other Places, to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute, Erect, and Appoint ſuch, and ſo many Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, Marts and Fairs, as ſhall in that behalf be thought fit and neceſſary.</p>
            <p>And further, alſo to Erect and Make in the Iſlands aforeſaid, or any part thereof, ſo many Mannors with ſuch Seigniories as to them ſhall ſeem meet and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient, and in every of the ſaid Mannors <hi>To Have</hi> and hold a Court Baron, with all things whatſoever, which to a <hi>Court-Baron</hi> do belong. And <hi>To Have</hi> and to hold <hi>Viewes of Franck-Pledge</hi> and <hi>Court-Leet</hi> for the Conſervation of the Peace, and better Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of thoſe Parts with ſuch Limits, Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Precincts as by the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven John</hi> Lord <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton;</hi> or their Heirs ſhall be Appointed for that purpoſe, with all things whatſoever, which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:187838:8"/>to a <hi>Court-Leet,</hi> or <hi>View of Franck-Pledge</hi> do belong, the ſame Courts to be Holden by Stewards to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted and Authorized by the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton;</hi> or their Heirs, or by the Lords of the Mannors and Leets for the time being, when the ſame ſhall be Erected; and becauſe that, in ſo remote a Country, and ſituate among ſo many bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Nations, the Invaſions as well of <hi>Salvages</hi> or other <hi>Enemies, Pirats,</hi> and <hi>Robbers,</hi> may probably be feared: Therefore we have given, and for us, our Heirs and Succeſſors, do give Power by theſe Prſents, unto the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle,
<note place="margin">Power to make War.</note> William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton;</hi> their Heirs and Aſſigns by themſelves, or their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, or other Officers, to Leavy, Muſter, and Train all ſorts of Men, of what Condition ſoever, or where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever born, whether in the ſaid Iſlands or elſewhere for the time being; and to make War, and to purſue the <hi>Enemies</hi> aforeſaid, as well by Sea as by Land; Yea, even without Limits of the ſaid Iſlands, (and by Gods aſſiſtance) to vanquiſh and take them, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken, to put them to Death by the Law of War, and to ſave them at their pleaſure, and to do all and every other thing which to the Charge and Office of a Captain General of any Army belongeth, or hath accuſtomed to belong, as fully and freely, as any Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain General of an Army hath ever had the ſame.</p>
            <p>Alſo, our Will and Pleaſure is, and by this our Charter, we do give unto the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton;</hi> their Heirs and Aſſigns, full <hi>Power, Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> in caſe of <hi>Rebellion, Tumult,</hi> or <hi>Sedition,</hi> (if any ſhould happen, which God forbid) either upon the Land within the Iſlands aforeſaid, or upon the <hi>Main Sea,</hi> in making a Voyage thither, or returning from thence, by him and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, their Captains, Deputies, or Officers, to be
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:187838:9"/>authority under his, or their Seals for that purpoſe. To whom alſo, for us, our Heirs and Succeſſors, we do Give and Grant by theſe Preſents, full Power and Authority to Exerciſe Martial Law againſt mutinous and ſeditious Perſons of thoſe parts, ſuch as ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to ſubmit themſelves to their Government, or ſhall refuſe to ſerve in the Wars, or ſhall fly to the Enemy, forſake their Colours, or Enſigns, or be Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, or Straglers, or otherwiſe howſoever offending againſt Law, Cuſtom, or Diſcipline Military, as freely, and in as ample manner and form, as any Captain Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of an Army by vertue of his Office, might, or hath accuſtomed to uſe the ſame.</p>
            <p>And our further pleaſure is, and by theſe Preſents, for us, our Heirs and Succeſſors: We do Grant unto the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord; <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton</hi> their Heirs and Aſſigns, and to the Tenants and Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the ſaid Iſlands, both preſent and to come, and to every of them, that the ſaid Iſlands, and the Tenants and Inhabitants thereof ſhall not from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth be held or reputed any Member or Part of any Colony whatſoever, in <hi>America,</hi> or elſewhere, now Tranſported or made, or hereafter to be Tranſported or made; nor ſhall be depending on, or ſubject to their Government in any thing, but be abſolutely ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated and divided from the ſame: And our Will and Pleaſure is, by theſe Preſents that they be ſeperated, and that they be ſubject immediately to our Crown of <hi>England,</hi> as depending thereof for ever.</p>
            <p>And that the Inhabitants of the ſaid Iſlands nor any of them ſhall at any time hereafter be compelled or compellable, or by any ways ſubject or liable to appear or anſwer to any Matter, Suit, Cauſe, or Plaint what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever out of the Iſlands aforeſaid, in any other of our Iſlands, Colonies, or Dominions in <hi>America</hi> or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, other than in our Realm of <hi>England,</hi> and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of <hi>Wales.</hi> And becauſe it may happen that ſome of the People and Inhabitants of the ſaid Iſlands, cannot in their private Opinions Conform to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:187838:9"/>Exerciſe of Religion according to the Liturgy, Forms, and Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or take or ſubſcribe the Oaths and Articles made and eſtabliſhed in that behalf; and for that the ſame by reaſon of the remote Diſtances of theſe Places, will as we hope, be no Breach of the Unity and Uniformity Eſtabliſhed in this Nation. Our Will and Pleaſure therefore is, and we do by theſe Preſents, for us, our Heirs and Succeſſors, Give and Grant unto the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton;</hi> their Heirs or Aſſigns, full and free Licenſe, Liberty, and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity by ſuch ways and means as they ſhall think fit to Give and Grant to ſuch Perſon and Perſons inhabiting and being within the ſaid Iſlands hereby, mentioned to be Granted as aforeſaid, or any part thereof, ſuch Indulgencies and Diſpenſations in that behalf, for, and during ſuch time and times, and with ſuch Limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Reſtrictions as they the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton;</hi> their Heirs and Aſſigns, ſhall in their diſcretion think fit and reaſonable: And that no Perſon or Perſons unto whom ſuch Liberty ſhall be given, ſhall be any way moleſted, puniſhed, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted, or called in queſtion for any differences in Opinion, or Practice in matters of Religious Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who do not actually diſturb the Civil Peace of the Iſland, County, or Colony, that he or they ſhall make their Aboad in. But all and every ſuch Perſon or Perſons may from time to time and at all times, freely and quietly have and enjoy his and their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Conſciences in Matters of Religion through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the ſaid Iſlands, they behaving themſelves peaceably, and not uſing the Liberty to Licentiouſneſs, nor to the Civil Injury nor outward diſturbance of others; any Law, Statute, or Clauſe contained, or to be contained, Uſuage or Cuſtom of our Realm of <hi>England</hi> to the contrary hereof in any wiſe notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. And in caſe it ſhall happen that any Doubt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:187838:10"/>or Queſtion ſhould ariſe concerning the true Senſe and Underſtanding of any Word, Clauſe, or Sentence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in our preſent Charter.</p>
            <p>We will Ordain and Command, That at all times, and in all things, ſuch Interpretations be made there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and allowed in all and every of our Courts what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever as lawfully may be adjudged moſt advantageous and favourable to the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton;</hi> their Heirs and Aſſigns.</p>
            <p>Although expreſs mention of the true yearly Value, or certainty of the Premiſes, or of any of them, or of any other Gifts or Grants, by us, or by any of our Progenitors or Predeceſſors heretofore made by the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle, William</hi> Earl of <hi>Craven, John</hi> Lord <hi>Berkeley, Anthony</hi> Lord <hi>Aſhley,</hi> Sir <hi>George Carterett,</hi> and Sir <hi>Peter Colleton;</hi> in theſe Preſents is not made, or any Statute, Act, Ordinance, Proviſo, Proclamation, or Reſtriction heretofore Had, Made, Enacted, Ordained or Provided, or any other Matter, Cauſe, or Thing whatſoever, to the contrary hereof in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>In Witneſs, whereof we have cauſed theſe our Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to be made Patents. Witneſs Our Self at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> 
                  <date>the firſt Day of <hi>November,</hi> In the two and twentieth Year of our Reign.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By Writ of Privy Seal.</hi> PIGOTT.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:187838:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
